No one is using Bumble.
This app was at the top of their game.
58 million users. A $2.2 billion
IPO. Over a billion in revenue.
Now, look at that stock graph.
Down 95%.
Revenue is falling, profit has
collapsed, and users are fleeing?
What happened?
As it turns out,
something much bigger is happening.
Dating apps across the board are dying,
and Bumble is the biggest loser.
To understand what happened, we need
to look at why Bumble worked. And that
brings us to its founder: Whitney Wolfe
Herd, who actually co-founded Tinder.
Reportedly, Herd gave Tinder its name and
logo, leading its aggressive marketing
on campus. Pretty pivotal.
Then, she was forced out.
A lawsuit quickly emerged, which eventually
led to a settlement of a bit over $1 million.
Sounds like a lot, but considering how big
Tinder was becoming, Herd was done pretty dirty.
But, she soon had another opportunity,
from Tinder’s rival: Badoo.
Andrey Andreev, the entrepreneur behind
the dating app with over 425 million
registered users worldwide, had spent years
trying to break into the American market.
With mixed results…
Then he saw the
lawsuit. Herd seemed like the perfect fit.
He wanted her to become Badoo’s CMO. But,
she pitched something else: Bumble.
This time, if two people matched,
the woman had to message first.
If you didn’t use these apps,
that might sound strange. Why do that?
To quote Herd herself:
[Whitney Wolfe Herd]: "What if women make the
first move, send the first message? And if they
don’t, the match disappears after 24 hours, like
in Cinderella, the pumpkin and the carriage? What
if we could hardwire that into a product?”
Andreev didn’t love the idea… but,
he trusted Herd.
He offered $10 million in funding,
but in exchange, he would own 79% of Bumble.
Though, Herd would have total creative control,
and Bumble could use Badoo’s software
infrastructure, a huge head start.
In just the first month, Bumble
passed 100,000 downloads.
In eight months, over 5 million
unique conversations in-app.
Then from 1 million downloads in 2015,
to 8 million the next year. To 12. To 17.
Revenue was climbing and passed 200 million.
Women loved this app, but so did a lot of men,
who often felt a lot of pressure
to make the first move on Tinder.
Plus, this was by design.
[Whitney Wolfe Herd]: ”I’m
so tired of this notion that women only need
to support women, why can’t we all support
each other? I’ve run into women who can be
highly problematic, detrimental and mean,
just like I’ve seen that in men.”
The one difference,
of women messaging first, really was huge.
Then, out of nowhere, came a road bump. A big one.
While Bumble was doing great, Andreev's empire was
imploding. But not for reasons you might expect.
As the PR was getting worse and worse,
Andreev sold his stake in MagicLab,
the parent of Bumble and Badoo,
to Blackstone for $3 billion.
Bumble was now owned by the world’s
largest private equity firm.
Though, Herd kept her 19% stake,
and the entire operation was merged
into Bumble Inc., with her as CEO.
I think Blackstone saw that the real
thing making money was Bumble.
So it worked out well for Herd,
and by now, Bumble was unstoppable.
It was America’s fastest-growing dating app.
Revenue jumped from $240
million to over $330 million.
Then, came the moment everything was
building toward: February 11, 2021. The IPO.
It started with shares priced
at $43, raising $2.2 billion.
The stock opened at $76, jumping
more than 76% in a single day.
Almost overnight, the market valued
Bumble at roughly $14 billion.
At 31, Whitney Wolfe Herd was now a billionaire,
and still with an 11.6% stake.
Everything was going great.
Then Bumble made a change,
and a critical one at that.
One which started a long chain of dominoes
that would lead to the app’s collapse.
Something strange happened after the IPO.
Just months later, on September 9th, 2021,
Bumble announced Blackstone would be selling
18,000,000 shares at $54 a share.
About a billion dollars.
So, why does this matter?
Well, it gives us some very important context.
Private equity firms like Blackstone Inc.
are built to buy companies, grow them fast,
then sell at the highest possible price.
That’s on top of the $2 billion of
shares it sold during the IPO.
Though it wasn’t all their shares
in Bumble… keep that in mind.
But investors began to think:
Maybe Bumble had already peaked?
And, in a way, they were right.
Nonetheless, this sent the stock down.
But Blackstone wasn't done… yet. Keep
them in mind for later.
In the meantime, there was
finally a bit of good news. In 2021, Bumble
Inc. reported $286 million in net income.
Its first profitable year ever.
Then in February 2023, Bumble forecasted
revenue growth, even above projections.
This was big, but something else made
this seem even better. Herd’s old
opponent: Tinder, was struggling.
Tinder, aka their parent Match
Group, forecasted revenue below
expectations. Their first ever quarterly decline.
While Bumble’s paying users increased 25% to 2.6
million; 147,000 growing quarter over quarter.
Tinder was falling off! At least,
that’s how it seemed.
So the board approved a $150
million stock buyback program.
Basically, they thought the market
undervalued Bumble, and this was big.
Showing they were succeeding while
Tinder struggled, pushed the market cap
from about $3 billion to $6.5 billion.
Not an all-time peak, but this was a great sign.
Maybe Bumble was just getting started?
Unfortunately, you might
notice the rest of the graph.
Tinder wasn’t really struggling. It was more
that the entire industry began to struggle.
Global dating app downloads had fallen from 287
million in 2020 to around 237 million by 2023.
A 17% drop in just three years.
Tinder's paying users started shrinking…
and kept shrinking, down to 9.3 million, with
quarterly revenue dropping to $491 million.
Match Group, Tinder’s parent company,
had lost nearly 80% of its peak value.
Then the same happened to Bumble.
A gigantic share drop in August.
So, what was happening?
Among college and graduate students in the U.S.,
79% said they weren’t using dating apps at all.
By 2023, around 61% of users
were between 30 and 49 years old.
I think many millennials, the generation that
helped dating apps explode, were slowly aging out
of app-based dating, while Gen Z weren’t as keen.
In late 2023, Herd stepped down from the
CEO role and was replaced by Lidiane Jones,
who led Salesforce’s Slack.
Herd might have been a good
visionary leader for Bumble, Jones… wasn’t.
She had big plans, but they were all pretty awful.
First, she laid off 350 employees.
Then just two months later, she announced
a new feature called “Opening Moves.”
For the first time in Bumble’s history,
women no longer had to message first.
Instead, women could post prompts on
their profile for men to respond to.
Not exactly the same as Tinder,
but it was pretty darn close.
"It's basically just Tinder now"
"Giving both parties the ability to
drive first engagement while pretending it's women
is a good way to have your cake and eat it too"
"The novelty of women initiating is
why I opened an account with Bumble;
take that away and Bumble will just fall out
of the circulation of apps I check in on"
I genuinely don’t know what
Jones was thinking. You need to
change things for sure, but, why do this?
Why remove what makes your app stand out?
Unfortunately for Bumble,
things were only getting worse.
We just passed 900,000 subscribers, and
I just want to say thank you all so much.
This ride has been awesome, and
we're almost at 1 million now!
Setup
Unsurprisingly, Bumble’s
market value had collapsed to around $1 billion.
Then, after just one year as CEO, Lidiane Jones
quit, along with Bumble’s CFO and CMO.
The entire leadership team behind the
rebrand was suddenly gone, leaving
Herd back in control as CEO.
[Whitney Wolfe Herd]:“I am deeply grateful
for the transformative work Lidiane has led
during such a pivotal time for Bumble, and her
leadership has been instrumental in building a
strong foundation for our future,”.
I’m pretty sure Herd was just
saving face for Jones here.
Regardless, she was back,
though she didn’t really want to be.
[Whitney Wolfe Herd]: "I had no intention
of coming back. Bumble needs me back. It's an
extension of me to some degree, and watching it
fall from its peak has been very hard."
She now had to clean up this mess,
and unfortunately, the industry
was in a pretty bad spot.
In just 12 months, Tinder, Bumble and Hinge
lost roughly 1.1 million users in the UK.
78% of Gen X, 80% of millennials and 79%
of Gen Z were burnt out of dating apps.
“Over time, the unfortunate misgivings of
being on a dating app can cause someone to
lose hope in the dating process
and finding the right person.”
But it gets worse.
By this time,
Blackstone had also cashed out big time.
They sold 11 million shares in 2023,
then another 11 million in 2024, each
time, the price per share dropping lower.
They had made about $2 billion from
the investment, though Bumble’s
stock was now down 94%.
And, we’re still not done.
Match Group had returned, even stronger.
Not with Tinder. But Hinge.
By 2025, Hinge was generating
$691 million in revenue.
Just seven years earlier,
it had made only $8 million.
The app had exploded to around
32 million users worldwide,
with nearly 2 million paying subscribers.
By this point, a date was being set up
on Hinge every two seconds.
So why was Hinge exploding?
Hinge had a unique goal:
Get the user to delete it.
Sounds weird, but the goal was to get the users
a successful relationship, so they could move on.
Instead of giving users unlimited swipes, the app
limited how many likes could be sent each day.
And this completely changed behavior,
because on Tinder… and Bumble,
many would just swipe on every profile.
Now, you had to be more intentional
about who you matched with instead of
mindlessly swiping hundreds of profiles.
Not only that, Hinge became
especially popular with Gen Z,
at least, those still using dating apps.
Almost half of its user base
is between 18 and 29. Plus,
many users are paying users.
So what did Herd do?
Layoffs, around 240 employees were
cut in a single wave, bringing total
layoffs to nearly 600 people in just 18 months.
Meanwhile, Bumble's user base had already fallen
from 58 million users to around 50 million.
Then came the bigger shift in three parts.
First, Bumble Inc. stopped trying to attract
everyone and instead only the “right people”.
Basically, Herd launched a major
overhaul. What she called a “Quality
Reset”. Removing all kinds of fake accounts,
or “low-intent” users who lowered the dating
experience and made it more “spammy”.
Next came killing the swipe entirely.
And with that change, Bumble also moved
entirely away from the very thing that
made it famous: women messaging first.
[Whitney Wolfe Herd]:"we will be basically
bottling the essence of what was always
meant to be women making the first move — a
confident experience, a safe experience,
a dynamic experience — to get you offline
in person on great dates and meetups.”
Jones had already somewhat removed that
dynamic by this point anyway, and this was
more an entire “reset” than what Jones did.
But, how would they do so?
Take a guess: AI
Now, instead of women or even men doing
the swiping, AI will become the matchmaker.
Specifically the in-app AI: Bee.
Oh boy…
Though, it wouldn’t “encourage”
AI-generated photos or messages, thankfully.
The AI tool will scan user
data to learn their values,
relationship goals, communication style,
and lifestyle through private chats.
Once Bee considers two people compatible, both
are notified in the app with a summary explaining
why they are a strong match.
But it doesn’t stop there.
Bumble is basically moving to a “date chosen
for you” instead of opting in or swiping. Like
scrolling on TikTok vs clicking a YouTube video.
Not that swiping was really that great a method
in the first place but annoying
to see another app move to AI.
Grand Payoff
Can Bumble turn things around?
Well, their Q1 2026 revenue
was also down as much as 14.1%.
But, earnings increased 165%.
It seems the era of high
growth is over. Now, Bumble is just
trying to stay alive and profitable.
Another app with an even stranger story is BeReal.
This app exploded, but it quickly disappeared.
Fans gradually got more and more annoyed
with it, but even stranger, the founders
seemed to have no plan on how to make money.
Click here to learn the rest of the story.